It's about life. It's about love. It's about us.
The Color Purple is a drama, history film directed by Steven Spielberg.
An epic tale spanning forty years in the life of Celie, an African-American woman
living in the South who survives incredible abuse and bigotry.
After Celie's abusive father marries her off to the equally debasing 'Mister' Albert Johnson,
things go from bad to worse, leaving Celie to find companionship anywhere she can.
She perseveres, holding on to her dream of one day
being reunited with her sister in Africa.
Albert, played by Danny Glover.
Celie, played by Whoopi Goldberg.
Shug Avery, played by Margaret Avery.
Sofia, played by Oprah Winfrey.
Harpo, played by Willard E. Pugh.
Nettie, played by Akosua Busia.
The Color Purple is a 1985 American epic period drama film, directed by Steven Spielberg
and written by Menno Meyjes, based on the 1982 novel by Alice Walker.
Spielberg's eighth film as a director, it marked a turning point in his career as it was
a departure from the summer blockbusters for which he had become known.
It is the first film directed by Spielberg for which John Williams did not
compose the score, which was done by Quincy Jones instead.
Jones also produced the film alongside Spielberg,
Kathleen Kennedy and Frank Marshall.
The film stars Whoopi Goldberg in her breakthrough role, along with Danny Glover,
Oprah Winfrey (in her film debut), Margaret Avery, and Adolph Caesar.
Filmed in Anson and Union counties in North Carolina, The Color Purple tells the coming-of-age story of a young African-American girl named Celie
Harris and the brutal experiences she endured including domestic violence, incest, child sexual abuse, poverty, racism, and sexism.
Upon its release by Warner Bros.
on December 18, 1985, The Color Purple was a box office success,
grossing $98.4 million against a budget of $15 million.
The film received generally positive reviews from critics, with praise going to its acting (especially Goldberg's performance), direction,
screenplay, musical score, and production values; criticism was directed by some for being "over-sentimental" and "stereotypical".
The film was nominated for 11 Academy Awards, including Best
Picture, but did not achieve a single win.
It holds the record for most Oscar nominations without one for Best Director.
It also received four Golden Globe Award nominations, with
Goldberg winning Best Actress in a Drama.
In 2006, the American Film Institute ranked the film 51st
on its list of the most inspiring movies.
The film explores themes of prison, rape, sibling
relationship, jazz, southern usa.
The tone is dark and thought_provoking and emotional.